it's easy to see why Edward Teach and his fellow pirates could be seen as pioneers of modern communications design, and why their deadly symbol -- (Laughter) there's more -- why their deadly symbol of the skull and crossbones was a precursor of today's logos, rather like the big red letters standing behind me, but of course with a different message. (Laughter) Yet design was also used to nobler ends by an equally brilliant and equally improbable designer, the 19th-century British nurse, Florence Nightingale. Her mission was to provide decent healthcare for everyone. Nightingale was born into a rather grand, very wealthy British family, who were horrified when she volunteered to work in military hospitals during the Crimean War. Once there, she swiftly realized that more patients were dying of infections that they caught there, in the filthy, fetid wards, than they were of battle wounds. So she campaigned for cleaner, lighter, airier clinics to be designed and built. Back in Britain, she mounted another campaign, this time for civilian hospitals, and insisted that the same design principles were applied to them. The Nightingale ward, as it is called, dominated hospital design for decades to come, and elements of it are still used today. But by then, design was seen as a tool of the Industrial Age. It was formalized and professionalized, but it was restricted to specific roles and generally applied in pursuit of commercial goals rather than being used intuitively, as Florence Nightingale, Blackbeard and Ying Zheng had done. By the 20th century, this commercial ethos was so powerful, that any designers who deviated from it risked being seen as cranks or subversives. Now among them is one of my great design heroes, the brilliant László Moholy-Nagy. He was the Hungarian artist and designer whose experiments with the impact of technology on daily life were so powerful that they still influence the design of the digital images we see on our phone and computer screens. He radicalized the Bauhaus Design School in 1920s Germany, and yet some of his former colleagues shunned him when he struggled to open a new Bauhaus in Chicago years later. Moholy's ideas were as bold and incisive as ever, but his approach to design was too experimental, as was his insistence on seeing it, as he put it, as an attitude, not a profession to be in tune with the times. And sadly, the same applied to another design maverick: Richard Buckminster Fuller. He was yet another brilliant design visionary and design activist, who was completely committed to designing a sustainable society in such a forward-thinking way that he started talking about the importance of environmentalism in design in the 1920s. Now he, despite his efforts, was routinely mocked as a crank by many in the design establishment, and admittedly, some of his experiments failed, like the flying car that never got off the ground. And yet, the geodesic dome, his design formula to build an emergency shelter from scraps of wood, metal, plastic, bits of tree, old blankets, plastic sheeting -- just about anything that's available at the time -- is one of the greatest feats of humanitarian design, and has provided sorely needed refuge to many, many people in desperate circumstances ever since. Now, it was the courage and verve of radical designers like Bucky and Moholy that drew me to design. I began my career as a news journalist and foreign correspondent. I wrote about politics, economics and corporate affairs, and I could have chosen to specialize in any of those fields. But I picked design, because I believe it's one of the most powerful tools at our disposal to improve our quality of life. Thank you, fellow TED design buffs. (Applause) And greatly as I admire the achievements of professional designers, which have been extraordinary and immense, I also believe that design benefits hugely from the originality, the lateral thinking and the resourcefulness of its rebels and renegades. And we're living at a remarkable moment in design, because this is a time when the two camps are coming closer together. Because even very basic advances in digital technology have enabled them to operate increasingly independently, in or out of a commercial context, to pursue ever more ambitious and eclectic objectives. So in theory, basic platforms like crowdfunding, cloud computing, social media are giving greater freedom to professional designers and giving more resources for the improvisational ones, and hopefully, a more receptive response to their ideas. Now, some of my favorite examples of this are in Africa, where a new generation of designers are developing incredible Internet of Things technologies to fulfill Florence Nightingale's dream of improving healthcare in countries where more people now have access to cell phones than to clean, running water. And among them is Arthur Zang. He's a young, Cameroonian design engineer who has a adapted a tablet computer into the Cardiopad, a mobile heart-monitoring device. It can be used to monitor the hearts of patients in remote, rural areas. The data is then sent on a cellular network to well-equipped hospitals hundreds of miles away for analysis. And if any problems are spotted by the specialists there, a suitable course of treatment is recommended. And this of course saves many patients from making long, arduous, expensive and often pointless journeys to those hospitals, and makes it much, much likelier that their hearts will actually be checked. Arthur Zang started working on the Cardiopad eight years ago, in his final year at university. But he failed to persuade any conventional sources to give him investment to get the project off the ground. He posted the idea on Facebook, where a Cameroonian government official saw it and managed to secure a government grant for him. He's now developing not only the Cardiopad, but other mobile medical devices to treat different conditions. And he isn't alone, because there are many other inspiring and enterprising designers who are also pursuing extraordinary projects of their own. And I'm going to finish by looking at just a few of them. One is Peek Vision. This is a group of doctors and designers in Kenya, who've developed an Internet of Things technology of their own, as a portable eye examination kit. Then there's Gabriel Maher, who is developing a new design language to enable us to articulate the subtleties of our changing gender identities, without recourse to traditional stereotypes. All of these designers and many more are pursuing their dreams, by the making the most of their newfound freedom, with the discipline of professional designers and the resourcefulness of rebels and renegades. And we all stand to benefit. Thank you. (Applause)
es fácil ver por qué Edward Teach y sus compañeros piratas podrían ser vistos como pioneros del diseño moderno de comunicaciones, y de por qué su símbolo letal, (Risas) hay más... por qué su símbolo letal del par de tibias y la calavera fue un precursor de los logotipos de hoy en día, más bien como las grandes letras rojas de pie detrás de mí, pero, por supuesto, con un mensaje diferente. (Risas) Sin embargo, el diseño también se usó para fines más nobles por una diseñadora igualmente brillante e igualmente improbable, la enfermera británica del siglo XIX, Florence Nightingale. Su misión era brindar asistencia sanitaria decente a todos. Nightingale nació en una familia británica muy bien situada y muy rica, horrorizada cuando se ofreció voluntaria para trabajar en hospitales militares durante la Guerra de Crimea. Una vez allí, se dio cuenta rápidamente de que más pacientes morían más por infecciones que se contagiaban allí, en las salas sucias, fétidas, que por las heridas de guerra. Así que ella hizo campaña para que se construyeran clínicas más limpias, claras y aireadas. De regreso en Gran Bretaña, condujo otra campaña, esta vez para los hospitales civiles, e insistió para que se aplicaran los mismos principios de diseño. El pabellón de Nightingale, como se denomina, dominó el diseño de los hospitales en las siguientes décadas, y los elementos que aún hoy se usan. Pero en ese entonces, el diseño se veía como una herramienta de la era industrial. Se formalizó y profesionalizó, pero se limitó a funciones específicas y generalmente en busca de objetivos comerciales en vez de usarse de manera intuitiva, como Florence Nightingale, Barbanegra y Ying Zheng lo habían hecho. En el siglo XX, este espíritu comercial era tan poderoso, que cualquier diseñador que se desviaban de él corría el riesgo de ser visto como raro o subversivo. Entre ellos se encuentra uno de mis grandes héroes del diseño, el brillante László Moholy-Nagy. Fue el artista y diseñador húngaro cuyos experimentos con el impacto de la tecnología en la vida diaria fueron tan poderosos que todavía hoy influyen en el diseño de las imágenes digitales que vemos en nuestras pantallas de teléfono y computadora. Él radicalizó la escuela de diseño Bauhaus en 1920, en Alemania, y sin embargo, algunos de sus antiguos compañeros le evitaban cuando quiso abrir una nueva Bauhaus en Chicago años más tarde. Las ideas de Moholy eran tan audaces e incisivas como siempre, pero su enfoque para el diseño era demasiado experimental, como su insistencia en verlo, como él mismo dijo, como una actitud, no como una profesión para estar en sintonía con los tiempos. Y, por desgracia, lo mismo se aplica a otro inconformista del diseño: Richard Buckminster Fuller. Otro diseñador visionario brillante y activista del diseño, completamente comprometido con el diseño de una sociedad sostenible, con visión tal de futuro que empezó a hablar de la importancia del ambientalismo en el diseño de la década de 1920. A pesar de sus esfuerzos, muchos diseñadores establecidos le tildaban rutinariamente de raro y, es cierto, algunos de sus experimentos fallaron, como el auto volador, que nunca llegó a despegar. Y, sin embargo, la cúpula geodésica, su fórmula de diseño para construir un refugio de emergencia con desechos de madera, metal, plástico, trozos de árbol, mantas viejas, láminas de plástico, con casi todo lo disponible en el momento, es una de las mayores hazañas del diseño humanitario, y ha dado el refugio tan necesario a muchas, muchas personas en circunstancias desesperadas desde entonces. Fue el valor y el entusiasmo de diseñadores radicales como Bucky y Moholy que me llevó a diseñar. Empecé mi carrera como periodista y corresponsal de prensa extranjera. Escribo sobre política, economía y asuntos corporativos, y podría haber elegido especializarme en cualquiera de esos campos. Pero elegí el diseño porque creo que es una de las herramientas más poderosas a nuestra disposición para mejorar nuestra calidad de vida. Gracias compañeros aficionados al diseño de TED. (Aplausos) Y mucho admiro también los logros de los diseñadores profesionales, que han sido extraordinarios e inmensos. También creo que el diseño se beneficia enormemente de la originalidad, el pensamiento lateral y el ingenio de sus rebeldes y renegados. Y estamos viviendo en un momento notable en el diseño, porque este es un momento donde ambos campos están cada vez más cerca. Porque incluso los avances muy básicos de la tecnología digital les han permitido operar de manera autónoma dentro o fuera de un contexto comercial, para alcanzar objetivos cada vez más ambiciosos y eclécticos. Por lo tanto, en teoría, plataformas básicas como el crowdfunding, computación en la nube, medios sociales, dan mayor libertad a los diseñadores profesionales y ofrecen más recursos para los improvisados y, con suerte, una respuesta más receptiva a sus ideas. Algunos de mis ejemplos favoritos están en África, donde una nueva generación de diseñadores está desarrollando tecnologías increíbles en la Internet de las Cosas para cumplir el sueño de mejorar la salud de Florence Nightingale. En los países donde más personas ahora tienen acceso a teléfonos móviles que a agua corriente y potable. Y entre ellos es Arthur Zang. Él es un ingeniero de diseño joven de Camerún que ha convertido una tablet en el Cardiopad, un dispositivo de vigilancia cardíaca en móvil. Se usa para monitorear el corazón de pacientes en zonas rurales remotas. Los datos se envían entonces a una red celular a hospitales bien equipados, a cientos de km de distancia para el análisis. Y si hay algún problema son vistos por los especialistas allí, Se recomienda un curso adecuado de tratamiento. Y esto, por supuesto, ahorra a muchos pacientes hacer viajes largos, arduos, costosos y a menudo inútiles a los hospitales. Y hace que sea mucho, mucho más probable que realmente se exploren sus corazones. Arthur Zang empezó a trabajar en el Cardiopad hace ocho años, en su último año en la universidad. Pero no logró convencer a fuentes convencionales de que invirtieran para poner en marcha el proyecto. Él publicó la idea en Facebook, donde un funcionario del gobierno camerunés lo vio y logró obtener una subvención del gobierno para él. Ahora está desarrollando no solo el Cardiopad, sino otros dispositivos médicos móviles para el tratar diferentes enfermedades. Y él no está solo, hay otros muchos diseñadores emprendedores con inspiración que también llevan a cabo proyectos extraordinarios solos. Y terminaré mostrando solo algunos de ellos. Uno es Peek Vision. Se trata de un grupo de médicos y diseñadores en Kenia, que han desarrollado una Internet de las cosas por su propia cuenta, como un kit portátil de examen de los ojos. Luego está Gabriel Maher, que está desarrollando un nuevo lenguaje de diseño que nos permita articular sutilezas de las identidades cambiantes de género, sin recurrir a los estereotipos tradicionales. Todos estos y muchos diseñadores más están realizando sus sueños, sacando lo mejor de su nueva libertad, con la disciplina de los diseñadores profesionales y el ingenio de los rebeldes y renegados. Y todos nos beneficiaremos. Gracias. (Aplausos)